A Finding Aid to the Maynard Walker Gallery Records, 1923-1975, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Maynard Walker Gallery records
1923-1975
Archives of American Art
Maynard Walker Gallery
AAA.maynwalk
Archival Resource Key
6.3 Linear feet
The records of New York City's Maynard Walker Gallery measure 6.3 linear feet and date from 1923 to 1975. The collection comprises personal and professional correspondence; artist's files for Thomas Hart Benton, John Chumley, John Steuart Curry, Lily Cushing, Madeline Hewes, Walt Kuhn, Wayne Williams, Grant Wood, and others; exhibition and gallery files consisting of printed materials, exhibition scrapbooks, a file on Spanish painting, and files for the exhibition Other Worlds (1945); financial and sales records containing files for artist accounts, non-artist accounts, bills of sale, and inventory; and photographic materials for exhibitions, works of art, and the writer Henry James.
Biographical / Historical
The Maynard Walker Gallery was an art gallery in New York, New York, founded by Maynard Walker in 1935. Walker previously worked for the Ferargil Gallery in New York where he began his professional relationship with the artists John Steuart Curry, Thomas Hart Benton, and Grant Wood. In 1938, Walker opened another gallery in Hollywood, California. Walker was a primary promoter of the Regionalists during the 1930s and 1940s. Walker retired in 1967 and died in 1985.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1929-1975 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Artist's Files, 1927-1972 (2.8 linear feet; Boxes 2-5, 7)
Series 3: Exhibition and Gallery Files, 1928-1970 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 5, 7)
Series 4: Financial and Sales Records, 1923-1967 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 5-6)
Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-1960s (0.5 linear feet; Box 6)
Scope and Contents
The records of New York City's Maynard Walker Gallery measure 6.3 linear feet and date from 1923 to 1975. The collection comprises personal and professional correspondence; artist's files for Thomas Hart Benton, John Chumley, John Steuart Curry, Lily Cushing, Madeline Hewes, Walt Kuhn, Wayne Williams, Grant Wood, and others; exhibition and gallery files consisting of printed materials, exhibition scrapbooks, a file on Spanish painting, and files for the exhibition Other Worlds (1945); financial and sales records containing files for artist accounts, non-artist accounts, bills of sale, and inventory; and photographic materials for exhibitions, works of art, and the writer Henry James.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Maynard Walker Gallery records were donated from 1974 to 1980 by Maynard Walker and in 1973 by the Frick Library on behalf of Maynard Walker. A portion of the collection was lent for microfilming and subsequently donated in 1976 by Maynard Walker.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on 35mm microfilm reels N697, 1603-1604, 2020-2025, 2159-2162, 2223, and 2424 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Scrapbooks; Regionalist (American Scene); Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State); Benton, Thomas Hart, 1889-1975; Curry, John Steuart, 1897-1946; Cushing, Lily Emmet, 1909-1969; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Kuhn, Walt, 1877-1949
- Correspondence, 1929-1975; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Arrangement
  The series begins with general correspondence arranged in chronological order and continues alphabetically starting with the letter C.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is with buyers, sellers, artists, and business and personal contacts such as Burt Lancaster, Paul Mellon, and Nelson Rockefeller regarding exhibitions, loans, sales, artworks, and general business dealings.
  - General, 1929-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
  - General, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - C-G, 1946-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Haverstick, Iola, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Henry Varnum Poor Memorial Scholarship, Regarding, 1968-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hirschl and Adler Galleries, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Identity of Artist of Painting of Woman, Regarding, 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - K-L, 1952-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - LaFarge, Margaret, 1946-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mc, 1945-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mellon, Paul, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nebraska Art Association, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rogers, Millicent, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - S, 1946-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - T, 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - W, 1954-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Watson-Gandy, Anthony, 1946-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The White House, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wood, Sara Bard Field, 1946-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Artist's Files, 1928-1970; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2.8 Linear feet Boxes 2-5, 7
  The series contains contracts, correspondence, insurance and shipping records, photographs of artwork, printed material, inventories, scrapbooks, and price lists for Thomas Hart Benton, John Chumley, John Singleton Copley, John Steuart Curry, Lily Cushing, Madeline Hewes, Winslow Homer, Walt Kuhn, Wayne Williams, and Grant Wood. See Series 4 for additional material on artists.
  - Aitken, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Folder contains photocopies.
  - Albright, Ivan Le Lorraine, 1927-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Allston, Washington, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1935-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Benton, Thomas Hart - Scrapbook, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Benton, Thomas Hart - Scrapbook, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Blakelock, Ralph, 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Boudin, Eugene, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bunting, J.D., 1951-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Callahan, Kenneth, 1946-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Carlsen, Emil, 1940-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chase, William Merritt, 1959-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Chumley, John, 1957-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32-35)
  - Chumley, John - Scrapbook, 1961-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Copley, John Singleton, 1931-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Cropsey, Jasper F., circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Cummings, Willard W., 1955-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Curry, John Steuart - General, 1930-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Curry, John Steuart - Disassembled Press Scrapbook, 1937-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Curry, John Steuart - Artwork Photograph Scrapbook, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Curry, John Steuart, 1937-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Curry, John Steuart - Scrapbook, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Cushing, Lily, 1953-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Dadd, Richard, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dasburg, Andrew, 1947-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Davies, Arthur B., 1962-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dickinson, Preston, 1937-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - DuJardin, Karel, 1955-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Eakins, Thomas, 1937-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Epstein, Jacob, 1946-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Feke, Robert, 1947-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gage, Merrell, 1956-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Glasier, Marshall, circa 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Grosz, George, 1939-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Heliker, John, circa 1955-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Henri, Robert, 1931-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hewes, Madeline, 1948-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Hill, Derek, 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hollander, Richard, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Homer, Winslow, 1940-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Ingres, Jean Auguste Dominique, 1929-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Iselin, Lewis, 1957-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Jackson, Jean Jones, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - James, Alexander R., 1936-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jamieson, Mitchell, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - John, Gwen, 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Kane, John, circa 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Kuhn, Walt, 1938-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
  - Kuhn, Walt, 1946-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
  - LaFarge, John, 1930-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lawson, Ernest, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - McBey, James, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - McBride, Henry, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Petty, Mary, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pittman, Hobson, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Quidor, James, 1947-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Raymer, Lester, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Renoir, Pierre-Auguste, 1952-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Rousett, Robert, 1951-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Steumpfig, Walter, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Taylor, Richard, 1941-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, 1948-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Truex, Van Day, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Trumbull, John, 1952-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Twachtman, Godfrey, 1960-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Vuillard, Edouard, 1945-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Watts, Jean, 1955-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Weir, J. Alden, 1960-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Whistler, Rex, 1941-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Williams, Wayne, 1957-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Wolfe, Tom, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Wood, Grant, 1935-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Wood, Grant - Scrapbook, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wood, Grant - Scrapbook, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Various Artists, Scrapbook, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Exhibition and Gallery Files, 1928-1970; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 5, 7
  Files in the series consist of catalogs and announcements, mainly for the Maynard Walker Gallery; clippings; correspondence, an annotated exhibition catalog, announcements, checklists, and clippings relating to the 1945 exhibition Other Worlds organized by Maynard Walker for the American British Art Center in New Britain, C.T.; and a file regarding Spanish painting.
  - Catalogs and Announcements, 1928-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1931-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition, Other Worlds (1945), Clippings, Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition, Other Worlds (1945), Correspondence, 1945-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition, Other Worlds (1945), Promotional Material and Lists, Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Scrapbook 1 (Parts 1,3,6, 7 of 7), 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
  - Exhibition Scrapbook 1 (Parts 2, 4, 5 of 7), 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Scrapbook 2, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Scrapbook 3, 1936-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - General, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Folder contains duplicates of material found in the collection.
  - Spanish Painting, 1948-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Financial and Sales Records, 1923-1967; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  The series contains sales and financial records for artists such as Lewis Iselin, Jr., Lily Cushing, Van Day Truex, Willard Cummings, and a few others, as well as records for non-artists, bills of sale by buyer name, and inventories. Files in Series 2 may contain additional financial and sales records for artists.
  - Artist Accounts, Jean Watts (Jean Jones Jackson), 1954-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Artist Accounts, Lewis Iselin, Jr., 1953-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Artist Accounts, Lily Cushing, 1948-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Artist Accounts, Tom Wolfe, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Artist Accounts, Van Day Truex, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Artist Accounts, Walter Stuempfig, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Artist Accounts, Wayne Williams, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Artist Accounts, Willard Cummings, 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Artist Accounts, General, 1947-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Non-Artist Accounts, 1946-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Bills of Sale, 1946-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24-28)
  - Bills of Sale, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Inactive Inventory of Items Sold, 1923-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Regular Inventory, 1947-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-1960s; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 6
  The series contains photographs and negatives of a Kenneth Callahan exhibition in 1952 taken by Oliver Baker, works of art grouped by artist name, and photographic reproductions of Henry James and his signature.
  - Exhibitions, circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Portrait and Signature of Henry James, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Works of Art, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8-20)